S2 Module 3: An Update on Lookups with Ariel Gabizon
Nico: Welcome to this module
of the ZK Whiteboard Sessions.
Today we're going to be
covering an update on lookups.
So this is a follow up to Module 6
in Season 1 with Mary Maller.
I'm Nico. I'll be today's host. And
with me today have Ariel Gabizon.
Hello, Ariel!
Ariel: Hey! Good to be here.
Nico: So, Ariel, what's the
plan for today's lesson?
Ariel: Well, today I'm going to start by
giving you an overview of the lookup landscape.
The different --
The three main approaches that
have been used in lookup protocols.
And then we're going to dive deep
into one of those approaches,
what can be called the "log derivative" approach.
Nico: Cool. Shall we get started?
Ariel: Yeah. Let's do it!
So let's look at the lookup landscape.
So we can think of three main approaches
that have been used in lookup protocols.
The first is what we can
call "multiset equality based".
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And in this category we have protocols like
the Halo 2 lookup protocol, the plookup protocol,
and slightly less known is a
protocol based on -- excuse me,
memory checking that appeared
in the Spartan paper.
And more recently, a GKR
version appeared in Lasso.
Nico: Okay. And so Halo 2 and plookup is in
the style of what we saw in Module 6. Right?
Ariel: Exactly. Yeah.
The second approach is what people
usually call the "log derivative" based.
And really this is one of those
names that are not too descriptive,
but have sort of a historical root.
That root, in a sense is these protocols
are sort of taking the log derivative from
what maybe is the original lookup
protocol from the ARIA paper,
but maybe a more descriptive name is
just lookups based on fractional sums.
Nico: Okay.
Do we need to understand what a log derivative
is to understand these or not at all?
Ariel: No. That's the nice thing.
You can talk about log derivative lookup
without knowing what a log derivative is. And --
Nico: This is a little more descriptive. Right?
Ariel: It's basically sums of fractions,
and we're going to see that later.
And in this category we have sort
of what you can say is the classic,
as people are calling it today,
logUp protocol that appeared initially in
the Bulletproof++ paper of Eagen et al.
But sort of, I think what's
become the standard reference is
this independent work of Haböck on this protocol.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So we had logUp and
then we had the cq protocol.
Nico: Of which you're an author?
Ariel: Yeah.
Which improved logUp, or you could say adapted
logUp to the setting of very large tables.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And we've had some
variants, cq+, cq++ and m-seek.
Nico: Some classic cryptography
naming happening here.
Ariel: Yeah.
Nico: A lot of plus and plus pluses.
Cool.
Ariel: Yeah.
And also --
And also here people have worked on using the GKR
to speed up certain aspects of the logUp protocol.
So this is the second approach.
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: The third approach, we can
call it maybe "matrix-vector" based.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: "Matrix-vector multiplication" based.
And I think the first --
The first lookup work in this
context was the Baloo work.
To a degree, Lasso also -- certain components
of Lasso also fall under this approach.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And in the folding context,
we have FLI, a recent paper.
Oh, and I sort of forgot to say that
also adapting the log derivative approach
to the folding context happens
in the ProtoStar paper.
Nico: Which I think is
mentioned in the folding module.
So that's a nice link here.
Ariel: Cool. So we have --
We have these basic -- these three approaches.
This is not comprehensive.
Some papers are not mentioned here and maybe
don't fall cleanly into these categories.
But in any case, today we're going to
focus on the log derivative approach
and dive deeply into sort of its
different variants, different versions.
Nico: Sounds good. Should we get into it?
Ariel: Yeah! Let's get into it.
So let me erase this.
Okay. So let's dive into
the log derivative approach.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: The approach is based on the
following basic lemma that says as follows.
So suppose -- let's fix vectors
f and t of size n over our field.
So again, we're thinking of this as the table is.
This is the witness that we want
to show is contained in the table.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: And let's assume the characteristic
of the field is larger than n.
Nico: What's the characteristic of the field?
Ariel: So the characteristic of
the field is the number of times --
the minimal number of times you
add one to itself to reach zero.
Nico: Is it -- is that the
number of elements in our field?
Ariel: Well, in a prime --
field of prime size it will be.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: But in a field of for example, size power
of 2, these fields have become popular lately.
The characteristic will be 2, even though
the fields can be of size 2^128.
Nico: I see. Okay.
Ariel: So the lemma says that it
gives us sort of a lookup criteria.
It says that f is contained in t if and
only if there exists a vector m of size n
such that we have the following
equality of rational functions.
So the equality looks like this.
On the left-hand side we have a sum over 1 to n.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: Of mᵢ over x plus tᵢ.
So sort of a fractional sum over
the table weighted by the mᵢ's.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And on the right-hand side we have
a fractional sum over the
values of f -- of the witness.
You can think of it.
Nico: Okay. And so what
does this equality tell us?
How does it link to our lookup problem?
Ariel: Right.
Well, so we're claiming here
that the existence of an m
such that this holds is an
equivalent condition for lookup.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And to gain some intuition,
let's at least sketch the proof.
So the easier direction is that
this is a necessary condition.
So suppose f is contained in t.
Let's do this little exercise.
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: How should we set the mᵢ's
so that this equality will hold?
Nico: Let's see. So it's a multiplier
on this thing. Right? So --
Ariel: Right.
Nico: Are we saying mᵢ is the
number of times fi appears,
or the number of times tᵢ appears in f?
Ariel: Exactly! Exactly.
We simply need to set mᵢ to be the
number of j such that fj is equal to tᵢ.
Nico: Okay.
So it's the number of repetitions.
Ariel: Exactly. Right? So --
Nico: Element of f appearing in t. Cool.
Ariel: Right.
So if for every index, for every
-- this fi is an element of t
and we just set these mᵢ's to
be the number of repetitions.
Right? Then obviously we will have this equality.
Okay.
Now the more interesting
direction is the other one.
And let's just sketch it.
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: So let me do it here maybe.
Nico: Sure. Let me move to the other side.
Ariel: All right.
Okay. So now let's assume that
f is not contained in the table.
So there exists on the right-hand side --
Nico: Something that appears zero times in here.
Ariel: Exactly.
There exists some --
Here, there's going to be some summand
1 over x plus a, where a is not in t.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So now the question is
-- So we have here this summand.
Can we somehow choose mᵢ's
that will create this summand?
Nico: Right.
So to pretend that it exists in here. Okay.
Ariel: Yeah.
And basically the idea is
that because the set of --
If we look at the set of functions of all such
functions 1 over x plus b over all b in the field,
so you can check that these
functions are linearly independent.
Nico: So no linear combination of these
will ever create the one that doesn't exist.
Ariel: Yes.
So if this a here is not
in t, no linear combination
on the left-hand side can give us this element.
So cannot --
So we cannot create 1 over x
plus a on the left-hand side.
Nico: Okay. And so is that why we're
using these rational functions,
because they have this property?
Ariel: Exactly.
The linear independence of these
functions is one of the main things
that makes them so convenient and useful.
So you may be wondering where
does this characteristic come in?
So suppose we had in f such an element a,
but the characteristic was 2.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So, how could we cheat?
Well, suppose now we try to use a vector
f where this element a that is
not in the table appears twice.
Then what's going to happen
here on this right-hand side?
Nico: Are they going to cancel out?
Ariel: Exactly.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So although we have an
element that's not in the table,
because the characteristic is very small,
the contributions of that element on this side are
going to cancel out and the prover could cheat.
Nico: I see.
Ariel: Okay. So now that we have the basic lemma,
let's use it to get a lookup
protocol, the logUp protocol.
So here's the idea for the logUp protocol.
We're going to start by having the
prover commit to this vector m.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: Which is --
Right. Which is the vector of
multiplicities, we can call it.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: How many times each element appears.
And then the verifier is going
to send a random challenge Beta.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And now the idea is, if the lookup is
not satisfied, if f is not contained in t,
that rational identity, with very high probability
it should not hold on the challenge Beta.
Nico: Right. This is our Schwartz–Zippel
testing that we usually have.
Ariel: Exactly.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: So now basically P is going to convince V
that the rational identity we
had in the lemma holds at Beta.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And by the way, how this step is done,
this is what separates the different
variants of the log derivative approach.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: It's different in
LogUp, in cq and in LogUp GKR.
Nico: But otherwise they
all follow this blueprint?
Ariel: Yes.
Nico: Cool
Ariel: All right. So let's start
with the -- with the logUp approach.
So the idea is that --
So this is all log or sort of.
We can call it just logUp, or "regular" logUp.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So how does step 3 work
in the "regular" logUp protocol?
So the idea is that -- so all this
now is sort of how to do step 3.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: So P will send a
commitment to a polynomial A.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And what is this polynomial A?
So here, like I said earlier, I'm going to sort of
interchange talking between
polynomials and variables.
So as a vector
Aᵢ, the i value of i is going to be, mᵢ
over tᵢ plus Beta minus 1 over fᵢ plus Beta.
Nico: Okay. Why are we building it this way?
Ariel: Well, if you recall the
rational identity we had --
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: There we had a left-hand
side and a right-hand side.
If we move the right-hand
side to the left-hand side.
Right. This is the i-th term of that identity
where the variable x is instantiated as Beta.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So according to the basic lemma, it
suffices now for P to show the following.
The first is that A's values are correct.
Nico: Correct with respect to m, t and f.
Ariel: Exactly. I mean, so in the
protocol, P sends a commitment to sum A.
Nico: Verifier doesn't know what it is.
Ariel: The verifier --
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: It's supposed to have these values.
The first thing is P needs to
show that these are really --
This is really the A --
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: -- he sent.
And the second thing, that
the sum of the Aᵢ's is 0.
Nico: And this is because of the identity where
we had some on the left, some on the right?
Ariel: Exactly.
So, given one --
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: If two holds, that exactly means that
the rational identity we saw in
the basic lemma holds at Beta.
Nico: Right.
Ariel: And again, since Beta was
chosen after P committed to m,
if the lookup condition does not hold, then with
very high probability, it won't hold at Beta.
So --
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: These two are sufficient to
prove f is contained in the table.
Nico: With very high probability.
Ariel: With very high probability over Beta.
Nico: Yes. Cool.
Ariel: All right. So how do we do 1 and 2?
So I'm going to mostly skip over 1.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And although we're going delve into
it a little when we talk about cq later.
Nico: Sounds good.
Ariel: But basically for now I'm going to, I
guess, brush it off and say that this is --
This part is sort of standard.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: It can be done with a quotient,
like we do many things in SNARKs,
or it can be done via Sum-Check.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: But let's focus on 2, because to do 2,
we're going to use another interesting
lemma that appears a lot in SNARKs.
What's called the Aurora -- what
I like to call the Aurora lemma,
since originally I saw it in the Aurora paper.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So let's see what the Aurora lemma is.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So the Aurora lemma tells us the following.
So, like we set up before, suppose H is a
multiplicative subgroup of order n, of size n.
Nico: Okay. So yeah, the roots of unity.
Ariel: Exactly. Yeah. And F --
Or let's say, let's call it A, A is a
polynomial of degree smaller than n.
Then if we look at the sum of A's values over
H, this is simply equal to 1 over n times A(0).
Wait, what's the n on the other
side? The 1 over n is here.
Nico: Sorry.
Okay. This looks very mysterious.
Ariel: Yeah. So this looks very magical.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: We can get --
Assuming A is of degree smaller than n,
we can get the sum of its values on
the subgroup simply by looking at A(0).
So let's see why this holds.
So we're going to look at
what's called a Lagrange base.
Nico: Yep.
Ariel: So let L₁ to Lₙ be the Lagrange base of H.
Nico: Which I think we cover in
Module 6 on lookups as well. So.
Ariel: Yeah. So, right --
So this is simply sort of these delta
functions, as they're sometimes called.
L₁(X) is simply the polynomial
of degrees smaller than n that
is 1 on the i-th point of H, g to the i.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: And 0 elsewhere on H.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So now given A, and A
is of degree smaller than n,
so I can write it -- the Lagrange basis, they are
basis for polynomials of degrees smaller than n.
So I can write A(0) --
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: As sum, and also what's --
When I write A in Lagrange base,
what is the i-th coefficient?
Nico: Do we know? We know the evaluations.
How do we get the coefficients?
Ariel: Well, that's what's
nice about Lagrange base,
that the i-th coefficient is just going to be --
Yeah. The i-th -- the value
of A at the i-th point of --
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: Of H.
So this is simply Aᵢ.
Nico: Right. Okay.
Ariel: Times Lᵢ of 0.
Nico: Right.
So you meant coefficient in this Lᵢ form.
I thought coefficient in the regular,
like a times x and b times x squared.
Ariel: Right. So when we --
Maybe I should have said this when
we talked about conventions earlier.
When we go between a vector to a polynomial,
then the values of the vector become the
coefficients of the polynomial when
we work with the Lagrange base of H.
Nico: I see. Cool.
Ariel: So in particular, A(0)
is just going to be --
Nico: This sum.
Ariel: This sum.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: And now we have this cool
sub-lemma which I'll leave as an
exercise, which tells us that
the Lagranges all agree at 0.
So for every i, Lᵢ(0) is simply 1/n.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So let's put this exercise in parentheses.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: And now, given this nice
fact, what does this sum become?
It simply becomes 1/n.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: Which we can take out --
Ariel: Times the sum of Aᵢ.
Nico: Right. And so we've
recovered what we wanted to prove.
Cool.
Ariel: Yeah.
So given this -
Right. What did we want to
show for the logUp protocol?
We wanted to show that the sum of
A's values on the subgroup is 0.
And now this Aurora lemma gives us
a very convenient way to do this.
So P will simply KZG open A(0) to zero.
Nico: Hopefully.
Ariel: Hopefully.
Nico: Right.
Ariel: And if he succeeds, according to the Aurora
lemma, then we have the sum on the subgroup is 0.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: And that implies with high probability
that the lookup holds. f is contained in t.
Nico: Amazing. So is that logUp complete?
Ariel: That is the regular
or basic logUp protocol.
And now we're going to look at
some variance optimizations.
So one variant we'll look at next,
what's called cq, is asking, well,
so far we've assumed the witness
and table are of the same size.
Nico: Yeah. This n that we've
been carrying around everywhere.
Ariel: Yeah.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: Right. But what if t, the
size of t, say instead of little n --
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: It's of some size big N
that is much larger than n.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And then the fascinating question is,
can we, after some pre-processing still run the
logUp protocol in time that depends on little n?
So can we still have prover
runtime depend only on little n?
Nico: Cool.
Nico: Cool. With a double question mark.
Ariel: Yeah!
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: And that's what we're going to see next.
Nico: Sounds good.
Ariel: So now in the context of this question,
let's start talking about the cq protocol.
That's going to be the next
main part of this lecture.
Nico: Sounds good. Shall we wipe what's here?
Ariel: Let's wipe.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: Okay.
So really, before describing cq itself,
the main theme that we're going to use
in cq has to do with committing to sparse
polynomials when we're using the KZG scheme.
Nico: Okay. What do we mean by sparse?
Ariel: All right. So let's --
Yeah. That's exactly what we're going to define.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: Let me actually remind everybody of a very
convenient property of the KZG
scheme, which is the additivity.
So I simply mean by this that
given commitments to f and g,
we have the property that if I want the
commitment of the polynomial f+g, this is --
I can --
I can simply get this by summing the commitments.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: So how does this tie
into sparse polynomials?
So first of all, what do I --
What do I mean by that?
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So suppose I have some set of polynomials.
So let's call them P₁ up to P,
let me use big N here.
And let's just assume that these like --
these polynomials are linearly independent,
though it's not crucial for what I'm going
to say next, but they always will be.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So now we say a polynomial P is little
n-sparse in the basis of the Pᵢ's in the --
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: If I can write P as sum
-- as a combination of the Pᵢ's
where Cᵢ is non-zero for at most little n i's.
Nico: Okay. So most of the time
this Cᵢ is going to be zero.
Ariel: Yes.
Nico: And then there's only n occurrences
where it's not and that's where it's sparse.
Ariel: Exactly.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: So now what's going to be very useful for
us is suppose we pre-compute
the commitments to the Pᵢ's.
So we --
Nico: So the big ones.
Okay. Yeah.
Ariel: Yes. We pre-compute
the commitments to these Pᵢ's.
So we can --
And now we want to compute the commitment to P.
So we think of Pᵢ's as something we know -- this
basis is something that we know of in advance.
But P is something we only get sort of
when the protocol has already started.
Nico: I mean, we can guess from
the big Ns and small ns that
you're using -- that probably this is
going to be our table stuff and --
Ariel: Yeah, yeah. Exactly.
So we can now compute the commitment to P.
So right.
If we write P as sum CᵢPᵢ, and
now we use the linearity of KZG.
So this is the same as sum of Cᵢ commitment of Pᵢ.
And only little n of these are non-zero.
Nico: Yep.
Ariel: So the point is that
when P is little n-sparse,
this requires only little
n-scalar multiplications.
Nico: Right.
Because most of the time the Cᵢ is
0, we don't have to do anything.
And when it is not 0, that's
when scalar multiplication.
Ariel: Exactly. Yeah.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So the cq protocol, you can think of it as
sort of going over the logUp protocol and noting
-- observing that all the polynomials that come
up are sparse in some basis we know of in advance.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So now let's sort of go over
some of the polynomials that come up
in the logUp protocol and see how
they have this sparsity property.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So just one little bit of again, notation.
So in the cq context, when we think of
the table is larger than the witness,
we usually also think of
having an additional subgroup.
So let's think of having also a
subgroup V of this size big N.
Nico: Right.
Ariel: And now let's maybe switch notation a
bit and use L to denote Lagrange basis of V.
Nico: So in the big set.
Ariel: Yeah. The big set.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: So the first polynomial that
comes up in logUp is this polynomial
m describing the multiplicities of the element.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So in the cq context,
when the table is very big,
we're going to encode m over the big subgroup V.
So m is going to be --
Now this polynomial sum mᵢ --
Nico: Right. And we do this over the big group
because in our identity we had the
sum of the m's divided by the t's.
So for every t there is an m.
And so this is why we need to be on the big group?
Ariel: Well, yeah, we need for --
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: First of all, yeah,
just to write down our table.
Nico: Right. We need this big group.
Ariel: We need this big group.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: Yeah.
So the first thing to notice is
that m is going to be little n.
So again, if we're still thinking of our witness
f as being a vector of size n or
equivalently a polynomial over --
So now let's call the
Lagrange base of H by the Bᵢ's.
So H we're still thinking of it
as a subgroup of order little n.
Nico: Okay?
Ariel: Right. So --
Okay. And maybe to make it clear, so now
we're thinking of t as a vector of size big N
or equivalently a polynomial where the
values are encoded over this bigger subgroup V.
Nico: Yeah. Cool.
Ariel: Yeah. And again, mᵢ's are
the multiplicities of the elements.
So what do you think? Is this
polynomial sparse in this basis?
Nico: I mean, if we have a honest prover,
only elements that are in here
will have m that is not zero.
Ariel: Right. Exactly.
Nico: Things that are not an f will
have 0, they appear zero times.
Ariel: Right.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So, exactly.
So m in this basis, since these describe
the multiplicities of the elements,
m in the basis of the Lᵢ's
will be little n-sparse.
So again to be --
The point is, like we said before, when
pre-computing the commitments to the Lᵢ's,
we can compute cm(m) in little n-scalar mults.
So --
Okay. So we see that the first polynomial
that comes up in the logUp protocol, we
can compute it even when the table is very large.
We can compute it after pre-processing with a
number of scalar multiplications
depending on the witness size.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: And now the second main
polynomial that comes up in logUp is --
So let's recall. Right?
And when we described the logUp protocol,
we said let's define this polynomial A
whose values in the logUp protocol
its values were something like this.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So in cq we sort of deal with
this part and this part separately.
And for the purpose of this talk,
let's focus on the table part.
That's going to be sort of the interesting part.
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: So let's assume --
Let's assume that this part just doesn't exist.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And now one of the things
we needed to do in logUp was --
Right. We need to show that
these are really A's values.
And before, during describing logUp we said well,
this is like a standard thing
with quotients or Sum-Check.
But now let's look a little how
this thing is done with quotient.
Like how do we usually prove
such a thing with quotients?
So what we can say is that A's vals
are correct if and only if there exists
a quotient polynomial Q such that --
So if I look at A times T plus Beta, then sort of
mod -- mod the subgroup, it is going to equal mᵢ.
So, so is he going to be equal
to ZV times Q of x plus m of x.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So, right.
So this is --
We know that if such a Q exists, it means that
for every -- whenever we plug in something from V,
this is the polynomial that vanishes on V.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: We're going to have that
A times T plus Beta equals m.
Nico: Okay. Because this goes to
zero when we plug in something --
Ariel. Yes. Yes.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: Or equivalently, A is equal to m divided
by T plus Beta, which is what we want to show.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So our goal is to compute the
commitment to Q like we did with m.
Our goal is to compute the commitment
with Q in little n-scalar multiplications.
Nico: Right. So again, it's this thing
of removing the dependence on big N.
Ariel: Yes. So, right, so the degree --
Nico: Yeah,.
Ariel: The degree of Q is definitely around big N.
Nico: Okay. Right.
Ariel: If you just look at the degrees here,
this is of degree big N or this
degree big N, bigger than this one.
So yeah.
So the degrees here are all big N.
But another point is, wait! Is it going to be
enough to compute just the commitment to Q?
Because really --
Because usually what goes on in SNARKs is we --
Nico: We are going to check
this at a random point?
Ariel: We're going to check
this at a random point.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So to check it at a random
point, like usually happens in SNARKs,
the commitment to Q wouldn't be enough for us.
We would need Q itself. Otherwise we wouldn't
be able to open it at a random point.
Nico: Right.
Because we need to evaluate it and
prove that we evaluated it correctly.
Ariel: Yeah.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: But a nice feature of KZG is that to check
an equation like this can be
done directly from commitments.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So this is another nice feature of
KZG that kind of follows from pairings,
from the fact that KZG is pairing-based.
And KZG can check --
We can check a degree 2 identity
directly from commitments.
Nico: Okay.
And here when you say degree 2, you're not
referring to the degree of the polynomials, right?
You're referring --
Ariel: I'm not.
I'm just saying say we think of the polynomials
as something we put in a variable. Right?
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So, right, so this is like --
This is a degree 2 --
Nico: Because we're multiplying two variables --
Ariel: Yeah. Right.
Nico: Okay. Cool.
Ariel: And this is also degree at most 2.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So this is sort of a black box
that I'm not going to get to here.
But this is again, it follows
from using pairings, and -- yeah.
So basically KZG and we have a degree
2 identity between polynomials.
We can check it directly from commitments
Nico: Without openings?
Ariel: Without openings.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: Yeah. It's a very cool feature.
Nico: Okay. So we're still
left with this problem, right?
How do we compute the commitment?
Ariel: And now what we need to do, we need to
find some basis that we'll know of in advance,
such that Q will be little n-sparse --
Nico: In that basis.
Ariel: In that basis.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: All right. So now let's see how
we can write Q as a sparse combination.
So for simplicity, let's sort of
forget for a second about some
of the details in logUp and just think of the --
of sort of the situation where we have A.
Nico: Yep.
Ariel: And A is little n-sparse in some basis.
Say in the basis of these Lagrange's .
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: And we want to write
A -- we have some fixed --
We have some fixed T. Right?
So T is the table polynomial set, and we
want to write A * T as Q * Z + R.
So sort of division with remainder,
division by Z with remainder.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: And we want to compute the
commitments to Q, to the quotient
and the remainder in little n-scalar mults.
And sort of -- the reason we can
do this essentially is because
since division is linear, the
sparsity is sort of inherited.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So to see what I mean by this,
let's just write this out in the basis Lᵢ.
So we know that A is sum AᵢLᵢ(X).
Again, we know that only little n
of these are non zeros.
Now let's pre-compute for each
Lᵢ the division with remainder.
So any Lᵢ we can write Lᵢ(X)*T(X).
And now divide with remainder.
So this is going to be some Qᵢ(X) times Z --
Nico: And some R.
Ariel: Plus some Rᵢ of X.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: All right. And division with remainder,
we mean here -- the point is that right
degree of Rᵢ is always smaller than --
That's what we mean by division, by remainder.
We're always computing Qᵢ and Rᵢ such that
the degree of this is smaller than this.
Nico: We take out as many Z's as we
can and then we're left with some R.
Ariel: We cannot write -- we can always --
We can always write this in this form
where the degree of the remainder
is smaller than the degree of Z.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: Otherwise it wouldn't be a remainder.
Nico: Yeah, yeah.
Ariel: And now the idea is just for
every i, we're going to pre-compute
the commitment to Qᵢ and the commitment to Rᵢ.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And now basically we're just going to use
the linearity of division with remainder. Right?
So we're just going to write this thing
-- we're going to plug in this thing.
So this is sum AᵢLᵢ(X) * T(X). Right?
Which is some Aᵢ(LᵢT(X)).
And now here we're going to plug in this
decomposition to quotient and remainder.
So we can write this as
sum Aᵢ(Qᵢ(X)*Z(X)+Rᵢ(X)).
And now let's sort of take out the Z.
So this is the same as sum AᵢQᵢ(X) * Z(X).
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: Plus some AᵢRᵢ(X).
Nico: Okay. So here you're
distributing the Aᵢ's over this?
Ariel: Yes.
Nico: And then keeping the Z out
because it doesn't depend on any i?
Ariel: Yes. Exactly. Right. And now we see that --
Nico: This looks suspiciously
like a division with remainder.
Ariel: Yeah. This is --
This is our Q.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: This is our R. And now are these
Q and R, are they sparse in some basis?
Nico: Well, if A is sparse, then we are sparse
in this Qᵢ basis and sparse in the Rᵢ basis.
Ariel: Exactly. We knew
most of the Aᵢ's were zero.
So it means that this Q and R, like A was
sparse in the original Lagrange basis.
This Q is going to be sparse in this Qᵢ basis
and the R is going to be sparse in this Rᵢ basis.
So if we pre-compute, this is why
cq is short for cache quotients.
These Qᵢ's, they're -- the commitments to these
Qᵢ's is what we call the cached quotients.
And we pre-compute them so that we can
then quickly evaluate the commitment to Q.
Nico: Amazing.
Ariel: All right. So that's
the basic idea of how cq works.
The drawback are all these
things we need to pre-compute.
Nico: Right.
Ariel: So, for example, we need to pre-compute
the commitments to these big N,
capital N number of these Qᵢ's.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So, for example, a setting --
The way I think of the numbers, we can
think, say of big N as 2^40 --
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And little n as 2^20.
And then we didn't go into how best to pre-compute
all these commitments, but the point is that
they can be computed in time in a number of
operations, which is O capital N log capital N.
Right?
So, for example, for this N, this
is like 40 times 2^40 --
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: Right? Which is about,
I don't know, 2^45.
And this is the amount of like, you need
this amount of scalar multiplications.
So this is --
When I try to estimate, this is a
computation that could take months.
Nico: Right.
And I guess a lot of storage as well, because
there's a lot of elements we need to keep.
Ariel: And the storage, I
think, is in the petabytes.
Nico: Okay. Wow.
Ariel: You need to store --
For the full cq, you need to store, I
think, seven times this number of elements.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And what do you get from that?
You get from that that you can use a 40 bit table
where regular logUp you could
probably use a 20 bit table.
Nico: I see.
Ariel: So how much better is a
40 bit table than a 20 bit table?
It's about a million times bigger.
Is it a million times better?
Nico: Right.
Ariel: Well, it depends on what the tables are.
And this is very much related to the whole notion
of table decomposability that was
highlighted in the Lasso paper.
So, for example, suppose --
Nico: Let's make some space.
Ariel: Yeah, let's make a little space.
I need maybe the whole board for this.
Yeah.
So, for example, suppose that the table
is just the table of 40-bit strings.
So as field values, the table is just
the value 0,1 up to 2^40 - 1.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So this is an example of what
we can call a decomposable table.
Why?
Because if we set T prime to
be the table of 20 bit strings,
so say the value 0 to 2^20 - 1.
Right? So what does that mean?
It means that some a is in T if and only if we can
write a as sum a₁ + 2^20 a₂,
where a₁ and a₂ are in T prime.
Nico: Right.
So actually, just to summarize this is --
We use these tables for range check, for example?
Ariel: Yeah.
Nico: Check that something is in 2^40.
Nico: And rather than looking up in this gigantic
table, we can look up in this one two things.
Ariel: Right.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So we see that, for example, for
this table, we can simulate a lookup in
it via two lookups to this table, T prime,
which might be -- which we don't need cq for.
We can work with regular logUp and sort of a
linear constraint, a linear combination gate.
Nico: So actually, even going back to Module 6,
where we had bit decomposition as our example,
it's kind of a hybrid of doing it
constraints only or lookup only.
Here we're doing somewhere in between.
Ariel: Yeah.
So in these tables that people are calling
decomposable, it's sort of like saying, well,
it's not 100% that a lookup in the big table
is simulated by lookups in the smaller tables,
but it's like a few lookups in the smaller
tables plus a minimal amount of constraints.
Say just a linear combination gate.
Nico: Yeah. Cool.
Ariel: So the more structure your table has,
the more you might not be motivated to
go through the painful sort of cq setup.
Nico: Right.
Ariel: So good use cases for cq are
when the table is just crazy values.
Just you have a set of 2^40. I don't
know, strings that look totally random.
Nico: Right.
No structure to them.
Ariel: Yeah. So those are the --
So those are the cases where
cq could potentially shine.
Okay. So now to end this lecture, I want to talk
a little about how GKR fits in this picture.
Nico: We hear Sum-Check GKR very often.
Ariel: Yeah.
So one sort of slightly painful point in logUp
or cq is the need to commit to big values.
So let's look a little at what sort
of values we had come up in logUp.
So we had the multiplicities mᵢ.
These are usually small numbers.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: If the witness --
Nico: it appears once, twice, three,
four times, and the witness, sure.
Ariel: Yeah. Their sum is going to be at most n.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: And say we could say that --
okay. Maybe also the values tᵢ are small.
I mean, that depends on the table.
But say for a table like this, they're
going to be small values. But what --
Nico: Small? We're saying
small compared to the field.
Ariel: Small.
Yeah. We're saying small --
Well, small compared to the field
and I guess sort of small --
Nico: In general?
Ariel: In general. Yeah.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: But where --
Yeah. Because their sizes will sort of
affect how long it takes to commit to them.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: Okay. But here is where sort of
there's something a little painful we have.
Right. We had these values.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: Yeah. Right.
This or maybe this plus 1 over fᵢ plus Beta.
But let's just look at this, for example.
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: It doesn't matter exactly.
The point is we had this big challenge
Beta. And so even if it wasn't big,
we're looking at the inverse of it. So.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: This is like if it's
a field of a certain size,
256 bits, say this is a full 256-bit
value, even if the mᵢ and tᵢ is small.
Nico: Right.
Ariel: So we would like ideally to avoid
committing, having to commit to these values.
Now why did we need to commit to them?
Our goal was to show things
like sum Aᵢ is equal to 0.
Nico: Yeah.
And that was also correcting these values.
Okay.
Ariel: Right. Right. But --
well, I mean, assuming --
Right, yeah --
Sorry.
What we want is to show -- we want to show for --
Okay. Or even going back to the full thing, right?
We wanted to show that this sum is 0. Right?
That's what we really wanted to show.
Nico: Yes. True, true.
Ariel: And the way we did it was
we committed to these values and
then showed that we really committed to
these values and that their sum is 0.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: But maybe there is some sort of
direct way just from the commitments that
we already have to m, t and f. Maybe there
is a more direct way without needing any
extra commitments like the commitment
to this A to show that that sum is 0.
And that is exactly what the
GKR protocol allows us to do.
Okay. So let's make some space so we
can say a few words about how GKR works.
Nico: Sounds good.
Ariel: So the idea in GKR--
Right, in SNARKs, we talk about circuits a lot.
So again, let's say we have
-- we have some circuit,
we have like an input, and we have a plus gate.
We have a mult gate, maybe. Right?
I don't know.
And usually in circuits, what we do is we
want to prove something about a circuit,
but we have the input values, but we also have
the intermediate values, the values of the gates.
And usually when we want to prove something
about a circuit, we're going to commit
not only to the inputs, we're going to
commit to all the intermediate values.
And sort of what GKR says is that when
our circuit is very, very structured,
we can prove something about a circuit output
while only committing to the input layer.
Nico: Okay. What do we mean by
very structured in this case?
Ariel: Well, so what is our case?
Right?
So our case is sort of like we
have inputs, let's call them --
Again, let's just for simplicity,
just look at the table part.
So we have, say -- looking at
a slightly simplified equation
than what we actually have in logUp,
we have, say, for example, inputs,
these multiplicities, m₁ to mₙ
and the table values t₁ to tₙ.
And we also had the challenge Beta. We had
the -- But let's say we just have these.
And let's say we want to compute --
We want the output to be this
fractional sum mᵢ over tᵢ.
Nico: Okay.
So here we're simplifying,
we're getting rid of the Beta.
Ariel: Yea. We're saying, say Beta
is 0, we're forgetting the f, but --
Nico: It would work in the same way.
Ariel: It would work --
It would work in the same way.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: So now we want a circuit where these
are the inputs and this is the output.
And sort of the point is in this LogUp GKR paper,
it's also explained, by the way, very
nicely in this paper called TaSSLE.
We can sort of compute this in a
circuit where what does simple mean?
So for GKR, sort of the ideal thing,
the simplest thing is when we have
a layered circuit and all gates
are just the same, the same gate.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: The same gate.
Nico: So layered mean we'd
have a gate with like 2 to 1
and then another layers of those
gates, 2 to 1 and then keep going?
Ariel: Yeah. So, for example, the
simplest thing would be a binary tree.
So we have, say, inputs --
So let's think of our input
sort of focusing on this case.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: Let's think of our inputs as being --
Let's interleave the m's and the t's.
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: So we have say m₁, t₁, m₂, t₂, blah blah
blah blah blah, m ₙ-1, t ₙ-1, mₙ tₙ.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: And now let's look at a circuit that
is sort of like you implied, is a binary tree.
Well. What's the word? Quadruple tree.
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: Four-legged tree.
So we want such a circuit where the
output in the end will be this sum mᵢ, tᵢ.
So what we want is sort of a
circuit that takes m₁, t₁, m₂, t₂.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: And outputs m₁ over t₁ plus m₂ over t₂.
But let's --
It's going to be convenient to think --
we want to get rid of these fractions.
So it'll be convenient to just think of
representing a fraction a/b as the pair (a,b).
Nico: Okay. And we keep the division for later,
or just for notation you were saying this?
Ariel: Well, so sort of inside the circuit --
Yeah, we could -- you say we leave it for later.
Inside the circuit we're
going to just all the time
operate by representing fractions in this way.
And then in the end you're going to get some pair.
Nico: I see.
Ariel: And you can then if you want --
Nico: Got you.
Ariel: Divide in the pair.
So, right, in this notation, this m₁, right?
Let's do a common denominator. Right?
This is going to be -- let's try to do some math.
Nico: m₁, t₂.
Ariel: Yeah. I think it's m₁, t₂.
Nico: m₂, t₁.
Ariel: Thanks. m₂, t₁ --
Nico: Over the product of the t's.
Ariel: And yes, I think it's t₁, t₂.
Nico: Yeah.
Ariel: So these gates, what are they going to be?
They're going to be gates sort of
mapping four elements into two elements.
Nico: Cool.
Ariel: From here to here.
And so GKR, it uses Sum-Check
in this recursive way.
But the point is when we have a circuit which is
like just a binary tree and the
gates are all the same. Right?
The gates are now these gates that take four
inputs like this and map them to two outputs.
And GKR works very well with such circuits.
And again its attractive feature
is that you commit to the inputs,
you don't need to commit to the values
coming up in these intermediate layers.
And yeah, maybe it is right. Maybe --
Right. Actually if you want just to see, we're
not like making it too easy on ourself, right?
If we just want to add this big Beta --
Nico: Sure.
Ariel: Right? That's not --
That's not going to be --
Well, maybe let's not mess up
the board by doing it explicitly.
Nico: Yeah. But I think we can imagine
how the Beta will appear here, here,
and then appear here, here,
and then in here and in here.
Ariel: Yeah, yeah, yeah. But let's
just not confuse. Let's remove it here.
Nico: Sounds good.
Ariel: Okay. So that is --
Yeah. That is how GKR can help us avoid committing
to big values while using the logUp protocol.
Nico: Can we combine the idea of cqs to -- of cq
to work with like this big N table and
the idea of using GKR or not really?
Ariel: I mean, that's --
Actually, that's a good question. I think I'm --
I need to think about it, but I think for sort of
the parts having to do with the witness, you can.
Nico: Okay.
Ariel: Yes. For the part sort of having to
do with a table with these cached quotients,
I think it doesn't really mix,
but yeah, the sort of the part we put aside,
the part of like the 1 over fᵢ plus Beta,
yeah, that you could do with
GKR also while using cq.
Nico: So does that conclude the session?
Ariel: That's it.
Nico: Amazing. Thanks.
Actually, let me try to summarize what
we saw just to bring things out together.
We first had a look at a map, kind of all the
lookup works that came out, and then we had a
deep dive into sort of logarithmic derivatives,
which you described as fractional sums.
And I think that's a lot more descriptive.
Ariel: Yeah.
Nico: And then within that space,
the original logUp protocol, then
pre-computation ideas with cq and big tables,
and now how to avoid commitments with GKR.
Ariel: Exactly.
Nico: Amazing.
Ariel, thank you so much! And to
the viewers, thanks for watching!